Guide to the Abraham Joshua Heschel Papers, 1880, 1919-1998 and undated RL.10086
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Public Activity, circa 1930s-1975 and undated; 4; 27 Boxes
  - Vietnam, 1953-1972; 6
    - Political, 1967-1971 (Box 70, Folder 6)
      Mix of materials including correspondence, clippings, handwritten notes, and posters regarding the conflicts in the Middle East and Vietnam. Also includes a draft letter to President Nixon regarding the Arab-Israel conflict.
    - [Political Advertisement - Vietnam], 1968 (Oversize-box 7, Folder 4)
      Contains full page ad, "A Call to Men of Conscience" in The National Catholic Reporter.
    - Publications, Clergymen and Laymen Concerned, 1968 (Oversize-box 2, Folder 6)
      Contains two bulletins of Clergymen and Laymen Concerned with the question "Who's Right? Who's Wrong? on Vietnam."
    - Vietnam, 1968 (Box 70, Folder 7)
      Mix of materials including press release in support of Hubert Humphrey for president, form letter from The Cantonsville Nine Defense Committee asking for financial and personal support, and a form letter from Daniel Berrigan regarding the trial of the Cantonsville Nine that is personally signed with a handwritten note at the bottom.
    - Vietnam, circa 1968 (Box 70, Folder 8)
      Mix of handwritten notes and annotated typescript related to a speech Heschel gave at the New York Avenue Presbyterian Church. Also includes related clippings and brochures.
    - [Clergy and Laymen Concerned About Vietnam], 1968-1969, 1972 (Box 70, Folder 9)
      Mix of materials including the agenda, list of participants, and correspondence related to the Cambridge Conference on the Future of the Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam, board minutes of the Central Conference of American Rabbis, and the history and bulletin of Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam.
    - ABM, 1969 (Box 71, Folder 1)
      A press release and a couple of newspaper clippings regarding the National Religious Committee's opposition to construction of the anti-ballistic missile system.
    - Amnesty, 1969 (Box 71, Folder 2)
      Corrected typescript of a speech together with a page of events for a Washington DC mobilization of clergy opposed to the war.
    - Vietnam, 1969 (Box 71, Folder 3)
      Primarily clippings related to Vietnam, but also includes clippings of events attended by Heschel.
    - Vietnam, 1969 (Box 71, Folder 4)
      Mix of materials related to protesting the Vietnam war including correspondence, printed flyers, clippings, and handwritten and annotated typescripts of several speeches. Includes a telegram from Daniel Berrigan to Heschel regarding Burton Weiss, a Jew who refused to be inducted into the Armed Forces and a letter from Senator Thomas Dodd.
    - Vietnam, circa 1960s (Box 71, Folder 5)
      Photocopied copied typescript with some original typescript inserts regarding a statement on the Vietnam War.
    - [Correspondence - Congress of the United States House of Representatives], 1970 (Box 71, Folder 6)
      Letter asking Heschel to participate in congressional inquiry on "War and National Responsibility" inspired by revelations of civilian massacres in Vietnam.
    - War Crimes, 1971 (Box 71, Folder 7)
      Several corrected and photocopied typescripts by Heschel which appear to be drafts of an editorial regarding the trial of Captain William Calley for his role in the My Lai Massacre. Also includes some correspondence related to Heschel's attempts to get it published.
    - Amnesty, 1971-1972; 1 of 2 (Box 71, Folder 8)
      Mix of correspondence, handwritten notes, and typescripts regarding amnesty for draft resisters during the Vietnam War. Includes two drafts of a speech Heschel made at the Interreligious Conference on Amnesty.
    - Amnesty, 1971-1972; 2 of 2 (Box 72, Folder 1)
    - NBC, 1972 (Box 72, Folder 2)
      Contains an assortment of handwritten notes, bulletins, and correspondence on a variety of topics. These include Heschel's participation in a program for Clergy and Laymen Concerned, a list of participants for the World Without War Council, and suggested questions for Heschel's scheduled appearance on a NBC Conversation Program.
    - McGovern, 1972 (Box 72, Folder 3)
      Mix of materials including correspondence, clippings and press releases related to both the anti-war movement and the election of McGovern. Also includes numerous letters and letters to the editor in response to two open letters Heschel wrote and were published in the New York Times related to his support of McGovern.
    - [Vietnam, McGovern], 1972 (Box 72, Folder 4)
      Mix of materials related to anti-Vietnam protests and the election of McGovern. Includes lists of participants, correspondence, and a statement of what the protesters represent.
    - Peace, undated (Box 72, Folder 5)
      Two page handwritten document on politics and morality.
- Restricted, 1936-1937, circa 1960s; 5; 1 Box
  This series contains ten folders of restricted materials which have been removed from their original location within the collection.
  RESTRICED: Access to these folders requires prior written approval. To request access, please contact Research Services prior to your visit.
  - [Correspondence], 1936-1937 (Box 308, Folder 1)
    Personal letters from Heschel to unknown recipient in which he talks about his life in Berlin, the challenges of publishing Die Prophetie, and meetings with Salman Schocken, Martin Buber, and Lion Feuchtwanger.
  - [Miscellaneous], 1941-1946, 1951-1952 (Box 308, Folder 4)
    Scope and Contents
    Sylvia Heschel correspondence.
  - [Sylvia], 1944, 1951 (Box 308, Folder 5)
  - Printed Matter, 1945-1947 (Box 308, Folder 6)
  - [Sylvia], 1946 (Box 308, Folder 7)
    Sylvia Heschel correspondence
  - [Correspondence], 1947-1948 (Box 308, Folder 8)
  - [Correspondence], 1947-1948 (Box 308, Folder 9)
  - Sylvia, 1947-1948 (Box 308, Folder 10)
- Writings, 1880, 1921-1990s and undated; 6; 245 Boxes
  The Writings series includes materials related to Heschel's books, articles, speeches, lectures, addresses, and other writings. This series also includes a large amount of Heschel's handwritten and typescript notes on a wide variety of topics and writings by other individuals. The Writings series contains six subseries: Addresses, Lectures, and Speeches, Articles, Books, Notes, Other Writings by Heschel, and Writings by Others. Detailed descriptions are below.
  - Addresses, Lectures, and Speeches, 1941-1973 and undated; 7
    Materials in this subseries document Heschel's reputation as a compelling and sought-after public speaker. The materials, including annotated and final drafts of addresses and lectures, handwritten notes, programs, clippings, and correspondence chronicle Heschel's numerous speaking engagements, lectures, and addresses at universities, synagogues, conferences, conventions, meetings, and local schools and organizations. Topics of these speaking engagements vary widely but include the Jewish communities of Eastern Europe, reform Judaism and practices, Jewish prayer, the Bible, the nature of God, and the ineffable. The folders are arranged chronologically.
    - Personal, 1941-1946, 1971-1973 (Box 73, Folder 1)
      Language(s): A few materials in Hebrew and Latin.
      Mix of materials including programs from speaking engagements and lectures, handwritten drafts of letters, clippings, and newsletters and bulletins about Heschel after his death. Also includes a list of Hebrew transliterations and a typescript of two scenes from a play featuring Hebrew Union College faculty presumably written by HUC students.
    - מזרח אירופה YIVO Lecture, 1945 (Box 73, Folder 2)
      Transliteration: Mizraḥ Eropah
      Translation: Eastern Europe
      Handwritten notes and an annotated typescript of a lecture given at YIVO on the Jewish communities of Eastern Europe. The typescript bears the title די מזרח אייראפעישע תקופה אין דער יידישער געשיבטע [The Eastern European Era of Jewish History].
    - JTS, 1945-1948 (Box 73, Folder 3)
      Materials include correspondence, programs from various events where Heschel was a speaker, and course lists at JTS. Includes handwritten draft from Heschel to Louis Finkelstein accepting appointment to the JTS faculty.
    - [Lectures], 1947-1950 (Box 73, Folder 4)
      Programs from various lectures given by Heschel between 1947 to 1950.
    - [Correspondence], 1947-1951; 1 of 2 (Box 73, Folder 5)
      A mix of event programs and clippings, synagogue bulletins, handwritten notes and correspondence related to Heschel's speaking engagements. Includes a handwritten itinerary for November and December 1950.
    - [Correspondence], 1947-1951; 2 of 2 (Box 73, Folder 6)
    - Least B, 1949-1958 (Box 73, Folder 7)
      Mix of handwritten notes, correspondence, and typescripts related to lectures and addresses given by Heschel. Includes typed address "The Courage to Remember" and a typed summary of a meeting of a Discussion of American Participants in Jerusalem Ideological Conference and Members of New York Jewish Agency Executive.
    - [East European Jews], circa 1950 (Box 74, Folder 1)
      Mix of handwritten notes and heavily annotated typescripts primarily on the topic of East European Jews. Appears to be for a lecture.
    - [Miscellaneous], 1951, 1957 (Box 74, Folder 2)
      Mix of materials including correspondence (letter from Yefroykin), program related to Heschel's speaking engagements, and a newspaper clipping.
    - [Miscellaneous], 1951-1952 (Box 74, Folder 3)
      Mix of materials including correspondence, programs, and clippings primarily related to lectures or addresses given by Heschel. Of particular interest are two letters from Marshall Meyer regarding a recent visit from Heschel and a letter from Julian Morgenstern thanking Heschel for his letter.
    - Symbolism, 1952-1953; 1 of 3 (Box 74, Folder 4)
      Mix of handwritten notes, fragments, index cards, and clippings regarding the topic of symbolism. Some of the notes may be for a talk Heschel gave on "Religious Symbolism" at the Conference on Science, Philosophy and Religion in 1952.
    - Symbolism, 1952-1953; 2 of 3 (Box 74, Folder 5)
    - Symbolism, 1952-1953; 3 of 3 (Box 74, Folder 6)
    - CCAR, 1953; 1 of 2 (Box 74, Folder 7)
      Primarily lightly corrected typescript likely for an address Heschel gave at a CCAR conference on the topic of Reform Rabbis and practices. Includes draft of a letter to Balfour Brickner (not sent) regarding the address.
    - CCAR, 1953; 2 of 2 (Box 74, Folder 8)
    - CCAR Copied, 1953; 1 of 2 (Box 75, Folder 1)
      Annotated typed drafts presumably of address Heschel gave at a CCAR conference.
    - CCAR Copied, 1953; 2 of 2 (Box 75, Folder 2)
    - Convention, 1953 (Box 75, Folder 3)
      Mix of handwritten notes, correspondence, journals, bulletins, and programs related to Heschel's address on prayer at the Rabbinical Assembly conference. Also includes the article "Conservative Judaism Faces the Need of Change: In What Direction, How Much, and How?" written by Fritz A. Rothschild.
    - Notes CCAR, 1953; 1 of 2 (Box 75, Folder 4)
      Primarily handwritten notes likely for an address Heschel gave at a CCAR conference on the topic of Reform Rabbis and practices. Includes letter and report from Rabbi Morton M. Berman who comments on the importance of the topic.
    - Notes CCAR, 1953; 2 of 2 (Box 75, Folder 5)
    - Prayer: Prayer Cleveland, circa 1953; 1 of 2 (Box 75, Folder 6)
      Primarily handwritten notes related to the to topic of prayer, possibly for a lecture in Cleveland. Also includes a copy of Heschel's address "The Spirit of Jewish Prayer" that has been clipped (sometimes into pieces) and annotated.
    - Prayer: Prayer Cleveland, circa 1953; 2 of 2 (Box 75, Folder 7)
    - Prayer: RA original order, 1953 (Box 75, Folder 8)
      Materials include a 34 page typed manuscript related to prayer, a corrected typescript of Heschel's keynote address "The Spirit of Prayer" given at the annual convention of the Rabbinical Assembly, a corrected typescript of Heschel's discussion of his paper, and a corrected typescript of his rebuttal to criticism's of his paper.
    - Radio, 1953 (Box 76, Folder 1)
      Materials related to Heschel's guest spot on WLIB radio program American Israeli Almanac.
    - Education, 1953-1954 (Box 76, Folder 2)
      Primarily correspondence related to Heschel's address on Jewish education he gave at the Jewish Pedagoic Conference and the article "The Spirit of Jewish Education." Also includes a written report and articles related to the conference.
    - RA, 1953-1954, 1965, 1971-1972 (Box 76, Folder 3)
      Correspondence related to a variety of topics including reaction to Heschel's address "The Spirit of Prayer" at the Rabbinical Assembly and translations of some of his books. Also includes a postcard from Cristina Campo to Sylvia Heschel.
    - [Schedule], 1953-1954 (Box 76, Folder 4)
      Three page handwritten list of dates for Heschel's lectures and speaking engagements between 1953 and 1955.
    - בני ברית, 1954 (Box 76, Folder 5)
      Transliteration: B'nai Brit
      Translation: Children of the Covenant
      Typed notes for Lecture I for a class by Heschel. Includes an outline of all the topics to be covered.
    - שבת, 1954 (Box 76, Folder 6)
      Transliteration: Shabat
      Translation: Sabbath
      Mix of handwritten and typed notes as if for lectures. Topics vary including spirituality, time, the essence of Judaism, and what is the world of biblical man?
    - שבת, 1954 (Box 76, Folder 7)
      Mix of handwritten and typed notes as if for lectures. Topics vary including space, time, and G-d.
    - [Miscellaneous], 1955-1956, 1961 (Box 76, Folder 8)
      Mix of materials including handwritten and typed notes as if for a lecture, an annotated typescript labeled "first draft of pref", and a review of God in Search of Man by Maurice Friedman.
    - [Miscellaneous], 1955-1958; 1 of 2 (Box 76, Folder 9)
      Language(s): A few materials in Yiddish, German, and French.
      Mix of correspondence, programs, bulletins, invitations, and clippings primarily related to events and lectures where Heschel was speaking or he attended.
    - [Miscellaneous], 1955-1958; 2 of 2 (Box 76, Folder 10)
    - YMHA II, 1956 (Box 76, Folder 11)
      Mix of typed and handwritten notes presumably for a lecture on the topic of religion at the YMHA in New York City.
    - Invitations Declined, 1956-1964; 1 of 2 (Box 77, Folder 1)
      Correspondence to Heschel regarding invitations to meetings, lectures, celebrations, writing articles, speaking engagements and writing reviews, all of which were presumably declined.
    - Invitations Declined, 1956-1964; 2 of 2 (Box 77, Folder 2)
    - Living, 1956-1957; 1 of 2 (Box 77, Folder 3)
      Mix of handwritten and typescript notes and fragments primarily related to the topic of living, possibly for various lectures. Includes other theological themes including the Bible and spirit.
    - Living, 1956-1957; 2 of 2 (Box 77, Folder 4)
    - [Correspondence], 1957 (Box 77, Folder 5)
      Correspondence and typescripts that are presumably for a lecture given in Toronto.
    - Jewish Education, Cantor, 1957 (Box 77, Folder 6)
      Contains two corrected typescripts written by Heschel. The first (untitled) is primarily regarding Jewish tradition, Jewish education, and Judaism. The second is an address "The Meaning of Jewish Liturgy" given by Heschel at the 10th Annual Conference-Convention at the Conference of Cantors.
    - [Miscellaneous], 1957, 1962, 1966, 1972 (Box 77, Folder 7)
      A mix of correspondence, publications, clippings and student papers. Includes "What We Might Do Together," an address given by Heschel at the National Convention of Religious Education Association.
    - Miscellaneous [JTS], circa 1957, 1964 (Box 78, Folder 1)
      Handwritten notes, many marked "JTS." Many of the note pages are related to the writings of other authors. Includes an address "Sacred Images of Man" given to the National Convention of the Religious Education Association and correspondence with the Anti-Defamation League. Also includes one newspaper clipping in Yiddish.
    - [Addresses], 1957, 1964, 1966 (Box 78, Folder 2)
      Contains three typed addresses given by Heschel: the Principal Address at [the] Americana Hotel Dinner on Religion and Race, "Jewish, Roman Catholic and Protestant Views of the Bible" as part of the lecture series entitled "The Bible - Antiquated and Contemporary" sponsored by the Women's Committee of the Seminary, and "On the Uniqueness of Jewish Existence" given at the Ideological Conference.
    - [Lectures], 1957-1958 (Box 78, Folder 3)
      Handwritten notes on a variety of topics including Kant, religion action and conviction, and heteronomy-theonomy-autonomy.
    - Lesser Ury, 1958 (Box 78, Folder 4)
      Handwritten notes, final draft of typed speech and short essay on a talk Heschel gave at the Lesser Ury exhibit at The Jewish Museum in New York,
    - Archive, 1958-1964 (Box 78, Folder 5)
      Mix of correspondence, bulletins, and clippings related to various speaking engagements and conferences attended by Heschel.
    - Invitations Declined, 1958-1965; 1 of 3 (Box 78, Folder 6)
      Correspondence which are all invitations to Heschel to speak. Some of the letters include a handwritten "No" while others have a typed response from Heschel.
    - Invitations Declined, 1958-1965; 2 of 3 (Box 78, Folder 7)
    - Invitations Declined, 1958-1965; 3 of 3 (Box 78, Folder 8)
    - [Program and Publication], 1959 (Oversize-box 2, Folder 3)
      Program from the "University of Life" at the Laurelton Jewish Center in which Heschel participated and "The Alumnus" newsletter from the Jewish Theological Seminary.
    - Old Age, 1959, 1961-1962; 1 of 2 (Box 78, Folder 9)
      Primarily correspondence requesting copies of or commenting on Heschel's address at the White House Conference Aging, but also includes clippings, press releases and bulletins related to the conference.
    - Old Age, 1959, 1961-1962; 2 of 2 (Box 79, Folder 1)
    - [Lecture notes], circa 1959; 1 of 2 (Box 79, Folder 2)
      Mix of typescript drafts and handwritten notes that appear to be lecture notes. Topics are varied including transcendence, memory, elliptic thinking, and the Bible.
    - [Lecture notes], circa 1959; 2 of 2 (Box 79, Folder 3)
    - G in Search lecture, circa 1950(?); 1 of 2 (Box 79, Folder 4)
      Primarily underlined typed lecture notes, but also includes handwritten notes and proof pages of excerpts from God in Search of Man and Man is Not Alone.
    - G in Search lecture, circa 1950(?); 2 of 2 (Box 79, Folder 5)
    - [G in Search lecture], circa 1950(?) (Box 79, Folder 6)
      Primarily underlined typed lecture notes, but also includes small amount of handwritten notes. Originals were in an unmarked envelope, but appear to be related to the G in Search lecture notes.
    - [God in Search of Man], circa 1950s; 1 of 2 (Box 79, Folder 7)
      Mix of handwritten and typescript notes and annotated excerpts from God in Search of Man and Man is Not Alone related to the topics of God, living, and World-View Biblical. Possibly for various lectures by Heschel.
    - [God in Search of Man], circa 1950s; 2 of 2 (Box 80, Folder 1)
    - Lectures, circa 1950s; 1 of 3 (Box 80, Folder 2)
      Handwritten notes on a variety of topics including revelation, philosophy of religion, faith, reason, and objectivity of religion.
    - Lectures, circa 1950s; 2 of 3 (Box 80, Folder 3)
    - Lectures, circa 1950s; 3 of 3 (Box 80, Folder 4)
    - Lectures, circa 1950s (Box 80, Folder 5)
      Handwritten notes cards for lectures on Knowing, Mystery, and the Shem HaMeforash--the perfect name of God.
    - Living copy, circa 1950s (Box 80, Folder 6)
      Mix of handwritten notes and annotated typescripts that appear to be for lectures on a variety of topics including radical amazement, mystery, and awareness of God.
    - Prayer: Prayer, circa 1950s (Box 80, Folder 7)
      Mix of handwritten notes and typescripts related to the topic of prayer, possibly for a lecture.
    - Prophets LA, circa 1950s (Box 81, Folder 1)
      Annotated typescripts possibly for lectures on the topics of The Prophets and Mishpat and Tsedakah.
    - AJC (American Jewish Committee), 1960 (Box 81, Folder 2)
      Mix of typed annotated drafts and final(?) typed address "The Moral Challenge to America", given by Heschel to the AJC 53rd Annual Meeting in April 1960. Also includes corrected transcript of "The Values of Jewish Education" by Professor Abraham Joshua Heschel.
    - Deeds Minnesota, 1960 (Box 81, Folder 3)
      Mix of handwritten notes, typescripts, quotes and source material most likely related to a lecture on deeds at the University of Minnesota where Heschel was a visiting professor.
    - [Newspaper Clippings], 1960 (Box 81, Folder 4)
      Clippings related to a variety of events including the White House Conference on Children and Youth, the American Jewish Committee Annual Meeting, and other speaking engagements by Heschel.
    - TI, circa 1960 (Box 81, Folder 5)
      A mix of handwritten notes, lecture notes, annotated typescripts and administrative documents related to Heschel's teaching at the Teacher's Institute.
    - Youth: [Appraising Ideals and Values in their Changing World], 1960 (Box 81, Folder 6)
      Handwritten notes, annotated drafts, and photocopies of final speech (originally named "Theme Assembly A" but changed to "Appraising Ideals and Values in their Changing World") presumably presented at the White House Conference on Children and Youth.
    - [Addresses], 1960, 1962 (Box 81, Folder 7)
      Contains four typed addresses by Heschel including "Appraising Ideals and Values in Their Changing World", "Religion and Race", "Idols in the Temple", and "Values in Jewish Education."
    - [United Synagogue Review], 1960-1961 (Box 81, Folder 8)
      Contains two United Synagogue Review publications. The first publication contains the article "Zionism and its role in Judaism" which includes excerpts from Heschel's address, and the second publication has "major moments" from the World Council of Synagogue convention in which Heschel attended and spoke.
    - Lectures, 1960-1961 (Box 81, Folder 9)
      Contains various transcripts including a transcript of the program broadcast "The House We Live In" in which Heschel was interviewed, a corrected transcript of an interview between Heschel and Rabbi Berkowitz, and transcripts of three lectures given by Heschel, "The Spirit of Judaism", a lecture on prayer, and "To Grow in Wisdom."
    - Washington, 1960-1961; 1 of 2 (Box 82, Folder 1)
      Primarily correspondence requesting copies of Heschel's address at the White House Conference on Children and Youth, but also includes clippings, new releases and an agenda for the conference. Also includes an agenda for the American Jewish Committee's 53rd Annual Meeting and Heschel's article "The Moral Challenge" in the Committee Reporter.
    - Washington, 1960-1961; 2 of 2 (Box 82, Folder 2)
    - Lectures Given, circa 1960-1962 (Box 82, Folder 3)
      Correspondence and handwritten notes related to lectures given at various place. Includes a handwritten itinerary of lectures for 1960-1961.
    - University of Minnesota Press, circa 1960-1962, 1964 (Box 82, Folder 4)
      Correspondence and contracts regarding the publication of a manuscript based on Heschel's lectures at the University of Minnesota.
    - [Miscellaneous], 1960-1965, 1971 (Box 82, Folder 5)